Guide to the George B. Darling Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- General Files, 1927-1991; Series I
  - Su-Sw (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Sadler, William, 1940-1944 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Seitz, Frederick, 1962-1986 (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Senn, Milton
    See: Series II, folders 87, 152
  - Seymour, Charles, 1950-1956, undated (Box 10, Folder 150)
    See also: Series II, folders 16, 113-114
  - Shigematsu, Itsuzo, 1983-1986 (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Shurr, Milton, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Smillie, Wilson G., 1936-1943 (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Smith, George H.
    See: Series II, folder 138
  - Smith, H. B., 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Snoke, Albert, 1961-1984 (Box 10, Folder 155-160)
    See also: Series II, folders 31-39
  - Society of Research Administration, 1974-1982 (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - Ta-Ti (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - To-Tu (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - Thoms, Herbert, 1951-1967 (Box 11, Folder 164)
    See also: Series II, folders 128-130, 142
  - Timothy Dwight College, 1956-1972 (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Tomlinson, William, 1961-1973, undated (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - Turner, Clair E., 1935-1966 (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - U-V (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - United States Army, 1927-1939 (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - United States Atomic Energy Commission, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 170)
    See also: Folder 187
  - University of Florida. J. Hillis Miller Health Center, 1952, 1957, undated (Box 11, Folder 171-172)
  - University of Maryland, 1947-1948, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 173)
  - University of Michigan, 1931-1972 (Box 11, Folder 174-175)
    See also: Folders 179-183
  - University of North Carolina, 1951-1952, undated (Box 11, Folder 176)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 177)
  - Vanderploeg, W. H., 1941-1943 (Box 11, Folder 178)
  - Vaughan, Henry F.
    - 1936-1944 May (Box 11, Folder 179)
    - 1944 June-1979 (Box 12, Folder 180-183)
  - Vaughan, Warren Taylor, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 184)
  - W (Box 12, Folder 185)
  - Wada, Sunao, 1959-1982 (Box 12, Folder 186)
  - Warren, Shields, 1950-1974 (Box 12, Folder 187)
  - Warren, Stafford, 1960-1971 (Box 12, Folder 188)
  - Waters, Levin, 1957-1975 (Box 12, Folder 189)
  - Weed, Lewis, 1943-1953 (Box 12, Folder 190)
  - Welch, Harold, 1952-1986 (Box 12, Folder 191)
  - White, Abraham, 1947-1973 (Box 12, Folder 192)
  - White, Colin, 1964-1967 (Box 12, Folder 193)
  - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1930-1931 (Box 12, Folder 194)
  - Wiggin, F. H.
  - Willard, William, 1951-1956 (Box 13, Folder 195)
    See also: Series II, folders 120, 128-130
  - Wilson, Hugh
  - Winslow, C.-E. A., 1948-1957, undated (Box 13, Folder 196)
  - Winternitz, Milton C., 1946-1957, undated (Box 13, Folder 197)
    See also: Series II, folder 81
  - W. K. Kellogg Foundation
    - General, 1932-1984 (Box 13, Folder 198-202)
      See also: Folders 24, 37, 71, 80, 84, 107, 130-131, 206
    - Semper Tenate Crew, 1984-1987 (Box 13, Folder 203)
  - Wong, Amy Chu, 1983-1986 (Box 13, Folder 204)
  - Wood, Carol, 1946-1966 (Box 13, Folder 205)
  - Wright, Zoe, 1943-1944 (Box 13, Folder 206)
  - Y-Z (Box 13, Folder 207)
  - Yale Club of New York, 1947-1972 (Box 13, Folder 208)
  - Yale University, 1958-1975 (Box 13, Folder 209-211)
  - Yamada, Setsuo, 1969-1973 (Box 14, Folder 212)
  - Darling annual holiday letters, 1946-1987 (Box 14, Folder 213-216)
  - Unidentified (Box 14, Folder 217)
- Yale Files, 1945-1957; Series II
  The arrangement of files in this series reflects George Darling's changing role in service to Yale University. The files are divided into two sub-series; the first, the Administrative files, include records Darling kept as director of medical affairs from 1946-1952. The second sub-series, Teaching files, documents courses Darling offered from 1953-1957.
  The Administrative files comprise the bulk of the series. They are arranged in alphabetical order by personal and corporate name. The files are indicative of the complex web ofassociations, committees, boards, and departments with whom Darling worked to coordinate medical affairs for the university. For an overview of the many issues Darling faced during his tenure, refer to the files for the Yale University Division of Medical Affairs and to the Yale University Council Committee on the Division of Medical Affairs. The University Council Committee on the Division of Medical Affairs was chaired by Reginald Coombe, and his correspondence delineates his understanding ofvarious situations.
  Because Darling was a central administrator in the university, there are substantial files of correspondence and reports with the president (Charles Seymour and A. Whitney Griswold), provost, treasurer, dean of the medical school (C. N. H. Long and Vernon Lippard), and other members of the university administration. Files for the various departments of the medical school, the school of nursing, department of public health, and department of university health include background information needed by Darling for planning purposes, but may also contain discussions of curriculum, budget, facilities, and personnel.
  Since Darling's position included oversight of Yale's affiliation with the hospital, there are numerous files for Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, particularly its executive director, Albert Snoke, and its executive committee. During this period the university and the hospital had to reach consensus on various issues involving complex legal and financial matters. These discussions culminated in a joint declaration of policy, a copy of which is included in folder 54, but which is the subject of extensive correspondence and meetings. The files also include notes and preliminary drafts to this declaration.
  The sub-series includes files for several medical organizations, both regional and national. Both the files for the Association of American Medical Colleges and National Fund for Medical Education relate to the common concern ofthe period over the high cost of providing training for students. The files for the Connecticut State Medical Society reflect more local concerns on these issues.
  Some of Darling's interest in curriculum development is documented in the files for the Committee on the Role of Human Biology and Ecology in University Education (folders 89-90) and the Executive Committee of the Study Unit in Sociology and Medicare (folders 109-110). However, the majority of material concerning Darling's courses in public health and nursing is filed in the sub-series Teaching files. Included are course notes, outlines, readings, and background materials, arranged by course number. Some materials appear to have been used in more than one course. This is particularly true for the class readings, which are, therefore, arranged by topic, rather than by course number and title, at the end of the series.
  - Administrative files
    - A (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - American Medical Association. Council on Medical Education and Hospitals, 1948-1950 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Association of American Medical Colleges
      - General, 1946-1951 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
      - Committee on the Costs ofMedical Education, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - B (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Black-Stevenson Cancer Foundation (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - C (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut (State)
      - General (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Governor, 1947-1950 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Governor's Committee on the Costs of Hospitalization of State Cases in State Aided Hospitals (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Connecticut Hospital Association (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Connecticut State Medical Society
      - General, 1947-1951 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Committee on Cooperation with the Yale School of Medicine, 1946-1952 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - D-F (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Eugene Higgins Trust, 1948-1952, undated (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital
      - General
        - 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 17-18)
        - 1948-1953, undated (Box 16, Folder 19-22)
        - [bed use--graphs], 1949-1952 (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - Assistant director [Nelson F. Evans], 1950 (Box 16, Folder 24)
      - Board of Directors [minutes], 1946-1949 (Box 16, Folder 25-26)
      - Building Committee, 1949-1951 (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - Building Fund, 1950-1951 (Box 16, Folder 28)
      - Citizens Committee (Box 16, Folder 29)
      - Committee on Financial Relations with Yale University, 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - Director [Albert W. Snoke]
        - 1946-1948 (Box 16, Folder 31-32)
        - 1948-1956 (Box 17, Folder 33-39)
      - Executive Committee
        - 1947-1951 (Box 17, Folder 40-44)
        - 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 45-46)
      - Financial Committee, 1947-1948 (Box 18, Folder 47)
      - Financial statements, 1946-1953 (Box 18, Folder 48)
      - Medical Social Service Department, 1946-1955 (Box 18, Folder 49-50)
      - Photographs, 1945, undated (Box 18, Folder 51)
      - Staffrosters, 1946-1955 (Box 18, Folder 52)
      - Grace-New Haven School of Nursing
      - General, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 53)
      - Nursing School Committee, 1954-1957 (Box 18, Folder 54-55)
    - H-J (Box 18, Folder 56)
    - Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, 1947-1949 (Box 18, Folder 57)
    - K-L (Box 18, Folder 58)
    - M-N (Box 18, Folder 59)
    - National Cancer Institute (D. S.), 1947-1952 (Box 18, Folder 60)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1947-1952 (Box 18, Folder 61-62)
    - National Fund for Medical Education, 1949-1954 (Box 19, Folder 63-65)
    - National Health Service (U. K.), 1950-1957 (Box 19, Folder 66)
    - New Haven Dispensary, 1946-1952 (Box 19, Folder 67)
    - New Haven Hospital Nursing Service (Box 19, Folder 68)
    - O-S (Box 19, Folder 69)
    - Redpath, Robert D., Jr., 1951 (Box 19, Folder 70)
    - Sheridan, Lewis Campbell, 1949-1950 (Box 19, Folder 71)
    - Sokal, Joseph E., 1951 (Box 19, Folder 72)
    - Spaulding, Keith, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 73)
    - U (Box 19, Folder 74)
    - United States
      - Public Health Service, 1946-1952 (Box 19, Folder 75)
      - Veterans Administration Hospital, 1946-1954 (Box 19, Folder 76)
    - University of Connecticut, 1947-1952 (Box 19, Folder 77)
    - W (Box 19, Folder 78)
    - Wallace, J. H. [I Remember When remembrances of the New Haven Hospital], 1949 (Box 19, Folder 79)
    - WiepQrt, Lucille, 1951-1952 (Box 19, Folder 80)
    - Winternitz, Milton C., 1947, undated (Box 19, Folder 81)
    - Y (Box 19, Folder 82)
    - Yale Institute of Occupational Medicine and Hygiene (Box 19, Folder 83)
    - Yale-New Haven Medical Center. Office of Program Development, 1954-1955 (Box 19, Folder 84)
    - Yale University
      - General
        - 1946-1954, undated (Box 19, Folder 85)
        - [mobilization during the Korean War], 1950 (Box 19, Folder 86)
      - Child Study Center, 1948-1949, 1953 (Box 19, Folder 87)
      - Committee on Honorary Degrees, 1951-1953 (Box 19, Folder 88)
      - Committee on the Role of Human Biology and Ecology in University Education
        - General, 1951-1953 (Box 20, Folder 89)
        - Background material, 1951-1953 (Box 20, Folder 90)
      - Department of Public Health
        - General, 1946-1957, undated (Box 20, Folder 91-97)
        - Cooperative Studies in Venereal Disease, 19471948 (Box 20, Folder 98)
      - Department of University Health
        - General, 1948-1952, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 99)
        - Division of Psychiatry and Mental Hygiene
          - General, 1946, 1949, 1951, undated (Box 20, Folder 100-102)
          - Ling, Thomas, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 103)
      - Division of Medical Affairs
        - Budget analysis and recommendations
          - 1950-1951 (Box 21, Folder 104-105)
          - 1953-1954
            See: Oversize, folder 1
        - Problem analysis outline (Box 21, Folder 106)
        - Reports, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 107-108)
      - Executive Committee of the Study Unit in Sociology and Medicare, 1954, 1955, undated (Box 21, Folder 109-110)
      - Institute of Human Relations, 1947-1952 (Box 21, Folder 111)
      - News Bureau, 1946-1951 (Box 21, Folder 112)
      - President
        - [Seymour,Charles], 1946-1950 (Box 21, Folder 113-114)
        - [Griswold, A. Whitney], 1950-1953 (Box 21, Folder 115)
      - Provost [Furniss, Edgar S.], 1945-1957 (Box 21, Folder 116)
      - School of Medicine
        - General, 1946-1956, undated (Box 21, Folder 117-118)
        - Ad hoc Committee to consider the role of the Yale Medical School in relation to national mobilization (Box 21, Folder 119)
        - Assistant dean in charge of post graduate medical education [Willard, William R.; Colbert, James W.], 1949-1952 (Box 21, Folder 120)
        - Business Office
          - [Davis, S. H., 1950-1951 (Box 22, Folder 121)
          - 1952, 1957 (Box 22, Folder 122)
        - Committee on Clinical Practice, 1945-1953 (Box 22, Folder 123-125)
        - Committee on Clinical Research and Teaching (Box 22, Folder 126)
        - Fund, 1946-1952
        - Committee on Physical Medicine, 1946-1948 (Box 22, Folder 127)
        - Committee on Post-Graduate Medical Education, 1947-1949 (Box 22, Folder 128-130)
        - Dean
          - [Blake, Francis; Long, C. N. H.], 1946-1948 (Box 22, Folder 131)
          - [Long, C. N. H.], 1949-1952 (Box 22, Folder 132-133)
          - [Lippard, Vernon], 1952-1957 (Box 22, Folder 134)
        - Dean's executive assistant [Bishop, Lottie], 1947, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 135)
        - Departments
          - Anatomy, 1947-1952 (Box 22, Folder 136)
          - History of Medicine, 1946-1953 (Box 22, Folder 137)
          - Immunology and Bacteriology, 1946-1950, undated (Box 22, Folder 138)
          - Internal Medicine, 1947-1955, undated (Box 22, Folder 139-140)
          - Microbiology, 1951-1953 (Box 23, Folder 141)
          - Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1947-1953 (Box 23, Folder 142)
          - Pharmacology, 1947, 1949 (Box 23, Folder 143)
          - Physiology, 1948, 1950-1953 (Box 23, Folder 144)
          - Preventative Medicine, 1946-1952 (Box 23, Folder 145)
          - Psychiatry and Mental Hygiene
            - 1947-1951 (Box 23, Folder 146)
            - [Friedgood, Harry B. The Science of Man, pp. 1-241], 1952 (Box 23, Folder 147-149)
          - Radiology, 1947-1948 (Box 23, Folder 150)
          - Surgery, 1947-1953 (Box 23, Folder 151)
        - Executive Board. Subcommittee on Clinical Sciences, 1951-1952 (Box 23, Folder 152)
        - Historical Library, 1946-1951 (Box 23, Folder 153)
        - Laboratory of Physiology, 1946-1948, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 154)
        - R. O. T. C. Unit, 1947-1950 (Box 23, Folder 155-157)
      - School of Nursing
        - 1946-1955 (Box 23, Folder 158)
        - 1956-1958, undated (Box 24, Folder 159-160)
      - Secretary, 1947-1957 (Box 24, Folder 161)
      - Service Bureaus, 1947-1953 (Box 24, Folder 162)
      - Treasurer's Office
        - General, 1946-1953 (Box 24, Folder 163-167)
        - History of financial agreements between the university and the hospital, 1918-1920, 1944-1945, 1946, undated (Box 24, Folder 168-170)
      - University Committee on Civil Defense, 1951-1952 (Box 24, Folder 171)
      - University Council
        - General, 1940-1950 (Box 24, Folder 172)
        - Committee on the Division of Medical Affairs
          - 1948-1949 May, undated (Box 24, Folder 173-176)
          - 1949 June-1954, undated (Box 25, Folder 177-182)
    - Yale University and the Grace-New Haven Community Hospital. Joint Declaration of Policy Concerning Mutually Supporting Programs ofProfessional Education and Patient Care and the Facilities Used Thereof, 1951-1952 (Box 25, Folder 183)
    - Z (Box 25, Folder 184)
    - Unidentified (Box 25, Folder 185)
  - Teaching files
    - Course notes
      - Nursing 320-321 (Box 25, Folder 186)
      - Public Health 101: Epidemiology, Microbiology, and Communicable Disease Center
        - 1953-1955 October 7 (Box 25, Folder 187-194)
        - 1955 October 14-1957 (Box 26, Folder 195-203)
      - Public Health 105: Public Health Seminar, 1955-1957 (Box 26, Folder 204-205)
      - Public Health 116
        - Policy Problems Related to the Health of the Public, 1953-1954 (Box 26, Folder 206-207)
        - Human Ecology, 1954-1957 (Box 26, Folder 208-213)
      - Unidentified (Box 27, Folder 214)
    - Class readings
      - General (Box 27, Folder 215)
      - Case books
        - #2: Environmental Sanitation (Box 27, Folder 216-217)
        - #5: Health in Underdeveloped Areas (Box 27, Folder 218-219)
        - #6: Population Problems (Box 27, Folder 220)
      - Education (Box 27, Folder 221)
      - Epidemiology (Box 27, Folder 222)
      - Fossil-agriculture land use (Box 27, Folder 223)
      - Philosophy (Box 27, Folder 224)
      - Welfare (Box 27, Folder 225)
      - Unidentified (Box 27, Folder 226-227)
- Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission Files, 1948-1972; Series III
  This series includes those materials which Darling chose to keep from his files as executive director of the ABCC. They are not official records, nor are they in any sense comprehensive. Darling's tenure in Japan is well-documented in the published annual reports, newsletters, and other publications of the ABCC, which are available in the Yale University Cushing/Whitney Medical Library. These should be used as primary sources before attempting to locate information in the scantier files available in this series.
  The series includes a few folders of background material consisting of copies of official documents from the late 1940s and early 1950s, which concern problems Darling would confront. Of most substance in this series are the six boxes of chronologically arranged outgoing correspondence from 1961-1972, the "Interoffice memoranda," and "Memoranda for the record." Virtually all correspondents included in the listing for Series I, are also recipients of letters in these boxes. Herbert Gardner, executive secretary of ABCC at National Research Council, is major recipient; there is an almost daily letter to him concerning the structure of ABCC, research results, employment issues, and project expansion. Darling directed similar letters to Charles Dunham, the chairman of the medical division of the NRC.
  Darling received numerous research proposals from university faculty and staffof other research institutions to undertake joint research ventures. While the files do not include the actual proposal, for the most part, Darling's studied responses to many are indicative of his interests in scientific and medical knowledge. The files include minutes of meetings with Japanese officials and formal reports submitted to the National Research Council on administration and research. There are also notes to staff and others on more mundane matters such as arrangements for sponsored events and entertaining, plans for social activities for American wives, travel plans for visiting dignitaries and friends, and arrangements for the Darlings' own trips. Darling's extensive travels and daily routine are documented in the folders of schedules and itineraries.
  A recurring theme in the correspondence and in other files in this series is the effort to work with the government of Japan to plan the future of ABCC operations. The United States wanted Japan to assume more responsibility for the commission, both politically and financially, and there are files dealing with budgetary issues, labor negotiations, and meetings organized to bring Japanese and American officials together to discuss concerns.
  The series is also useful for those interested in Japan's perception of the work of the ABCC. Darling had members of his staff prepare translations of local newspaper stories concerning the commission. These translations are in "Press coverage, Japanese." Additional translations are filed in "Correspondence."
  Included in the series are a few files relating to Darling's receipt of an award from the United States Atomic Energy Commission and his retirement. A summary of Darling's accomplishments in Japan is included in the honorary volume published in 1972. (Darling's own writing on his term as executive director is included in Series IV.)
  - Administrative services, personnel, 1968-1969 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Background files, 1948-1956 (Box 28, Folder 2-6)
  - Budget position paper, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Budget reduction estimate [appendix History ofEfforts to Increase Japanese Participation"], 1968 July 13-26 (Box 28, Folder 8-9)
  - Correspondence
    - 1961-1962 (Box 28, Folder 10-17)
    - 1963-1966 February (Box 29, Folder 18-32)
    - 1966 March-1968 June (Box 30, Folder 33-46)
    - 1968 July-1969 (Box 31, Folder 47-59)
    - 1970 February-1971 June (Box 32, Folder 60-75)
    - 1971 July-1972 September 15 (Box 33, Folder 76-93)
    - 1972 September 18-December (Box 34, Folder 94-96)
  - Future operation of the ABCC, 1967-1972 (Box 34, Folder 97-99)
  - Honorary volume, 1972 (Box 34, Folder 100)
  - Informal meeting on ABCC, 1969 June 18-19 (Box 34, Folder 101)
  - Interoffice memoranda, 1965-1972 (Box 34, Folder 102)
  - Japanese Advisory Council, 1972 (Box 34, Folder 103)
  - Labor Union, 1966, 1971-1972 (Box 34, Folder 104)
  - Memoranda for the record, 1962-1969 (Box 34, Folder 105)
  - Notes, 1957-1972 (Box 34, Folder 106)
  - Orientation material to Japan and ABCC, 1956-1971, undated (Box 35, Folder 107)
  - Personnel chart, 1970
    See: Manuscript Common Folio, Box 4, folder 78
  - Press coverage, Japanese
    - 1957-1968 August (Box 35, Folder 108-118)
    - 1968 September-1972 June (Box 36, Folder 119-135)
    - 1972 July-November (Box 37, Folder 136-138)
  - Progress report
    - Director's summary, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 139)
    - Life span, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 140)
    - Adult health study, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 141)
    - Epidemiology, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 142)
  - Research design and program components for FY-60 [estimated budget], 1959 (Box 37, Folder 143)
  - Retirement as executive director, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 144)
  - Schedules and itineraries, 1957-1970, undated
  - United States Atomic Energy Citation [invitation, program, press coverage], 1970 (Box 37, Folder 148)
    See also: Series VI, folder 78
  - United States-Japan Conference on ABCC, 1969 June (Box 37, Folder 149)
  - United States Public Health Service [non-position paper"], 1968 (Box 37, Folder 150)
- Writings, 1920s-1979; Series IV
  The files are arranged in chronological order.
  This series includes articles, speeches, and other writings and public statements by George Darling. An individual file may contain notes, drafts, and a printed copy of the work. The earliest item in the series is a work of fiction composed by Darling as a student, while the latest is a tribute to Darling's mentor Henry Vaughan.
  Most of the material in the series concerns Darling's years in Japan. Of particular note are the files for Darling's report for Detlev Bronk on the ABCC. This is a lengthy draft, which includes a review of problems confronting the agency and attempts to solve them. There are also numerous brief statements written by Darling for special occasions. The series does not include all the published reports of the ABCC which included remarks by Darling as the executive director. These works are available in the Cushing/Whitney Medical Library.